Guide to the John Leonard Miller Papers and Oral History Interview
Special Collections, University of Washington Libraries
John Leonard Miller papers and oral history interview
1923-1986
University of Washington Libraries Special Collections Box 352900 Seattle, WA 98195-2900
2240
Miller, J. L. (John Leonard)
4.11 cubic feet 7 boxes plus 2 sound cassettes
Political activist, labor movement leader
John (Jack) Leonard Miller was born on November 3, 1889 in Dayton, Kentucky. At 12 he left home and traveled around the country hoboing and taking odd jobs. He worked as a coal miner in Danville, Virginia and a harvester in the Midwest. Because of his interest in worker's rights, Miller joined the United Mine Workers while in Virginia. He joined the Socialist Party while he was in Canada and the Industrial Workers of the World (IWW) in 1916. He moved to Seattle in early 1916 and was on board the Verona during the Everett Massacre of November 1916. He married Violet Wilson in 1924. After settling down Miller had a number of jobs and began writing. He continued to rally for workers rights and upon his retirement took up lobbying for fair treatment of senior citizens. In addition, he gave lectures and interviews regarding the Everett Massacre, and wrote short stories. He died at age 96 in 1986 of a heart ailment. He was the last living survivor of the Everett Massacre.
Organized into 5 accessions.
Accession No. 2240-001, John Leonard Miller oral history interview, 1974
Accession No. 2240-002, John Leonard Miller papers, 1982
Accession No. 2240-003, John Leonard Miller papers, 1923-1986
Accession No. 2240-004, John Leonard Miller typescript,
Accession No. 2240-005, John Leonard Miller papers, 1953-1975
Oral history interview, biographical features, correspondence, financial records, writings, newsletters, clippings, ephemera, manuscripts. Most of the material concerns the Everett Massacre and Industrial Workers of the World.
Open to all users.
Miller, J. L.$q(John Leonard)$vInterviews; Labor unions$zWashington (State); Labor union members$zWashington (State); Labor$zWashington (State); Labor movement$zWashington (State); Records (Documents); Oral histories; Labor Archives of Washington (University of Washington), $e host institution; Miller, J. L. (John Leonard)$vArchives; Socialist Party (U.S.); Labor Archives of Washington (University of Washington); Industrial Workers of the World; White House Conference on Aging, State of Washington (1981: Yakima); Coal miners$xLabor unions; Everett Massacre, Everett, Wash., 1916; Personal Papers/Corporate Records; Labor Unions; Labor History; Mines and Mineral Resources; Washington (State)
- John Leonard Miller oral history interview, 1974; 2240-001; 2 sound cassettes (80 minutes)
  Tape recorded interview conducted by Richard Berner on 11 March 1974, covering the years of his youth through 1918.
  Interview concerns his youth and his activities in the Midwest and Canada as a United Mine Workers organizer and a member of the Socialist Party, and in Washington as a member of the Industrial Workers of the World. The interview focuses on the Everett Massacre.
  Listen to the audio recording of this interview on the Libraries Digital Collections site.
  Open to all users.
  Donated by John Leonard Miller, 3/11/1974.
- John Leonard Miller papers, 1982; 2240-002; 3 pages
  Notes from interview conducted by Meta Buttnick in 1982.
  Notes are about the IWW street demonstrations and speeches in Everett by Jewish Wobblies, Oct and Nov 1916.
  View selections from this collection in digital format.
  No restrictions on access.
  Donated by Meta Buttnick, 10/1/1982.
- John Leonard Miller papers, 1923-1986; 2240-003; 3.33 cubic feet 5 boxes
  Biographical features, correspondence, financial records, writings, newsletters, clippings, ephemera.
  The bulk of this accession is amateur creative writings, but Box 1 does contain "The Everett Massacre as Seen By Its Last Survivor". A few other autobiographical pieces are present.
  Records stored offsite; advance notice required for use.
  Donated by Nylene Schoellhorn, 10/7/1986.
  - Biographical Features, 1980-1986 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1923-1986 (Box 1)
  - Financial Records, 1970-1975 (Box 1)
  - Writings of Miller including "The Everett Massacre As Seen By Its Last Survivor," autobiographical pieces, short stories, and poems, approximately 1920-1986 (Box 1-4)
  - Writings of Others, 1974-1983 (Box 4)
  - Legislation, 1976 (Box 4)
  - Journals/Appointment Books, 1973-1980 (Box 4)
  - Newsletters, 1964-1986 (Box 4)
  - Publications, 1898-1976 (Box 4)
  - Clippings, approximately 1950-1986 (Box 4-5)
  - Ephemera, 1961-1986 (Box 5)
  - Subject Series, 1976 (Box 5)
  - Columbia Club, Seattle, 1972-1975 (Box 5)
  - Elder Citizens Coalition of Washington, King County Unit, 1973-1976 (Box 5)
  - U.S. White House Conference on Aging, 1981, 1980-1981 (Box 5)
- John Leonard Miller typescript, 2240-004; .42 cubic foot (1 box)
  Typescript, mainly of a novel; undated
  Donated by Nylene Schoellhorn, 9/1/1994.
- John Leonard Miller papers, 1953-1975; 2240-005; 0.36 cubic feet 1 letter sized document case
  Manuscripts and reminiscences of John "Jack" Miller's early life, as well as a topical manuscript on "The Hobo" and a variant title: "The North American Hobo." Includes accounts relating to Miller's members in the Industrial Workers of the World and participation in the Everett Massacre of 1916.
  Donated by Jeremy Egolf, who Miller had given the collection to. 2017-09-13
  - You & How You Came To Be, 08/17/1953 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Journal to Nylene Winette Schoellhorn, 08/17/1953 (Box-folder 1/2)
  - Memories Not Memoirs, 02/26/1984 (Box-folder 1/3)
  - Hobo Defined, 1953-1975 (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Making Of Hobo, 1953-1975 (Box-folder 1/5)
  - The North American Hobo, 1953-1975 (Box-folder 1/6)
  - We Never Forget, 1953-1975 (Box-folder 1/7)
  - Correspondence, 1973-1975 (Box-folder 1/8)
  - Misc. Writings, 1953-1975 (Box-folder 1/9)
  - Family History, 1953-1975 (Box-folder 1/10)